welcome to voices with raviki
i am joined again by my friend brent
cooper uh brent is here
uh to bring a a very uh welcome
perspective
uh i i often say that brent and i don't
agree on everything but
brett shows up in authenticity and good
faith and i think he is deserving of the
same
and i hope that he feels that i'm
extending that back to him uh so
welcome brent and could you please uh
maybe give a short
very short reintroduction of yourself
and then i'll introduce the topic we're
going to start with
yeah thanks for having me back i'm a
political sociologist uh a rogue one at
that
and um uh very engaged
in the uh in the literal and
sociological sense
and um kind of uh in limbo
right now for various reasons but um
all the more reason to engage on this
particular
subject um which is
metanoia as you're gonna give your
introduction
so um brett i'm gonna talk to you about
how i have used the word
in my work and what it and how i
understand it and then
that will hopefully give something as a
foil for you to enter into discussion
with
uh so um you know the term for me
is gone out of uh sort of the of a
for me a christian or origin it comes
from the new testament
uh the metanoia it's often translated as
conversion
it's a very poor translation especially
um
you know in 2020 in which the notion of
conversion
has gone through sort of american
protestantism and met this particular
kind of
you know emotional experience um
but if you go back to the original
meaning of the word and especially to
its neoplatonic heritage
meta of course means beyond uh to get to
something
uh of sort of the the structuring
principles of something
like metaphysics you're not talking
about physics you're talking about the
structuring
principles of physics and then neue is
of course from the greek
nueces uh and you're probably aware of
this
i've made arguments that noises
correspond to what i call perspectival
knowing
um and uh and so what what's being
talked about
is a kind of transformation in which the
principles
that structure your perspectival knowing
what you find salient and relevant
have been deeply tra and permanently at
least long-standingly
transformed and that's why the metaphor
of turning
because what happens when i turn is i
have this perspective in which these
things are relevant and salient
and then i turn this way and the now i'm
in another perspective when things are
relevant and salient
and then the idea is that's a metaphor
something analogous that
can happen to people uh when they're
undergoing
a transformation and these kinds of
transformation have historically been
called
i think have something to do with wisdom
on one hand or have something to do with
and that this term is
very contested and very vague uh but
spirituality in another
and so i i we sort of ended last night
and we were sort of
bridging the topic of um the
spirituality
of of what you've been talking about and
then you propose metanoia
as a bridging point between if you'll
allow me this from the sociological
analysis
and the spiritual practice and so that's
how i'm seeing it and that's why now now
i'd like to hear
what you want to say about that yeah
that's a great setup um i just want to
issue a quick
correction if if if i'm right i think
the um
the the more true definition of the term
is conversion whereas it's been
translated in the bible as repentance
yeah at times at times yeah and so so
the the research
that i've that have aggregated basically
says that the bible
mistranslated translates it as
repentance which
i it's not completely wrong and so yeah
repentance and guilt and all that is
very useful in this concept but it
describes
metanoia more broadly as conversion um
the ways the ways you did describe it
and so
that's an important framing in the first
place
like that it's that uh this you know
that comes through the christian
tradition
um sort of manifest in repentance but
the deeper meaning
is conversion and the that's what the
scholarship suggests is that there's a
deeper meaning
yeah and i've not found any uh sources
for metanoia exactly outside of
outside of greek and outside of the
bible it's that it all points back to
that
but i wouldn't say that it's necessarily
exclusive to that
either you know oh no we're trying to
always when we when we
historicize too and when we try to
reinvent
a contemporary metaphysics we're trying
to uh disambiguate and abstract the
meaning
from these historical meanings uh but
then also contextualize in our
in our current moment our current
unfolding of history
and so um you know then the nesting in
christianity
is is important but i don't want anyone
to
to think that it's exclusive to that
especially because
christianity has been so hegemonic and
the christian religion you know um
it emerged but it also was
institutionalized
by different powers that be over time
much of it after the fact like much of
this historical writing
of of um the of the time of jesus and of
ancient greece even
of alexander the great much of the
writing that has survived
was hundreds of years after the fact
there's not real
tangible history but we but it's it's
taken as such
uh typically until it's deconstructed
and so um you know i've gravitated
towards this term for
for a long time uh especially
you know um about eight years ago 2012
uh my my research in metamodernism was
just
really around this meta prefix and
whatever that
whatever i fell into that bucket right
and so
um um
uh metaphysics and metanoia especially
was something that i thought was
under under uh explored and analyzed
and internet modernism you mean you was
being underexplored
within just in general just in general i
mean even at that time meta modernism
hardly existed as a as a discourse right
um
but but so so i went through my own kind
of
spiritual conversions and um
you know in in the uh the paper that
i've been writing
you know i cite on one hand there's some
authors that say metanoia is very rare
it only happens
once twice maybe three times in your
life and
certainly in in in a grand sense it
would be that rare
but then there's another example i give
of a ted speaker
who says oh you have you know tens of
thousands a hundred thousand metanoias
in your life because they're focusing on
the other end of the spectrum just
little novel changes
and so um you know we gotta we gotta
play with that spectrum but i'm i'm
leaning towards the more
substantive changes but i i i'm
prefacing that because i've also had
lots of little changes in my life
so right so when i say conversion it's
not that i converted to christianity or
from christianity
for example i grew up secular and uh
you know interested in you know secular
humanism
as a kind of contemporary scientific
civil religion uh if you're part of that
tradition at least
and you know and so you know you talk
about the religion without a religion
and all that but like all of this is
preceded by
pluralism and a kind of study of world
religions
yeah and uh so there's a revive revived
interest in
uh in religion and mythology but
it's all and as far as i'm concerned
it's all a dead end unless you're trying
to weave those threads together
into into a uh you know try to parade
them into a meta narrative and so the
world religions are all part of a common
tradition
of humans discovering and creating
religion
and so so i i have my own sort of
metanoias
within the christian tradition but then
also beyond that and political social
political
economic personal metanoias
and the the research i did has taken me
across all these fields
such that the the term has been um
by people like peter senge has been
introduced into business
right and so um but there's still a lot
of work to be done
to again to weave those threads back
together
because they're all inconclusive
essentially so there's a couple things i
want to pick up on
um so there was three things he said the
first was you know that uh
i think uh there's a vacancy point i
think that metanoia sits within a family
uh family resemblance idea of related
things so whereas you may not have
you know i mean you may not have a term
sort of
like it etymologically or syntactically
i think buddhist notions of
enlightenment i think enlightenment is
also that kind of
deeply transformed transformation of
one's perspective
noticing and what one finds deeply
salient and relevant
and so i think that's and i think if we
so
i think if we broaden the scope to think
of that uh you know the family
resemblance class
um awakening is another one awakening is
very much
like you you're in this and you go to
that right um
and so i i agree with you i think if we
open up and look at
rather than trying to find a strict
definition
if we collect this family resemblance
together then i think we can start to do
what you're talking about i think we can
both
abduce what is perhaps general or
universal
uh but also also specify what is
historically and culturally specific
and i think we can do both of those so
on the second point
the idea of the spectrum uh i i i don't
know if you know this the work i'm doing
with dana greg
i argue explicitly for that and andrew
newberg has done
um that as well um in his book um
uh so how enlightenment affects your
brain this is the idea that there being
a continuum
uh between the machinery of insight into
things like the flow experience
and mystical experiences which i do
experimental work on and then full-blown
awakening experiences in which people
not just have a mystical experience but
they feel called to transform themselves
in response to that and so i think
there's a continuum there
and i i think remembering the continuum
is very important because
we just talked about this and over here
enlightenment and
people will spa right but if you make
them realize deeply
the continuum then its relevancy and
currency to them
is more much more apparent much more
apparent
and then the third thing is more of a
maybe a question
um uh so you've sort of brought out two
aspects of something
and very often people put them in
in a relationship of debate i'm aware of
this within
uh cognitive science and philosophy and
if you'll allow me two terms
you won't mention one already pluralism
but the one that is often opposed to it
is perennialism uh the idea that there
is they're all saying that ultimately
the same thing
now i would i think you do too i reject
perennialism
i think there's something right about
pluralism but there's also the idea
that that doesn't mean there aren't
universal things because
i think one of the things that
distinguishes pluralism from mere
relativism
which gets incommensurability and all
kinds of you know self-destructive
patterns in
is that pluralism says that while there
is considerable variation like we just
discussed
there are nevertheless universal
processes in terms of which we can
understand and compare and bring these
things into dialogue where do you stand
on that perennialism yeah
yeah i appreciate that that's a good
question i i don't think i
would reject perennialism um i
i think they i think they can it can be
compatible with
let's say pluralism right we don't we
can juxtapose them without canceling
each other out um it's a good word i
should have
invoked it before um because it is this
there's many ideas within perennialism
um
uh but just the you know it's a deep
subject but just the idea itself
i i like the kind of universal religion
because religions are
so um historically and materially
you know predicated and and constituted
and we often forget that like all that
survives is the myths right and we
forget about the
geography and all these essential things
and
of course as i alluded to in the
beginning like we can't forget how much
of history has been lost or destroyed
you know like just ballpark 99
of like documents of the ancient world
is gone
but um before going further i wanted to
give a plug to this book
um uh from i think from 2018
um by bloomsbury it's called metanoia
a speculative ontology of language
thinking in the brain
oh and that was it's referenced it's
referenced briefly in my
draft that i sent you but um you know um
it's it's probably i don't actually draw
on it a lot
but it's probably the the best book on
the subject and the most
coincidentally the closest to your
research interests
and so there's a ton of good stuff in
there so if we if we do converse on that
more we could use this a book like this
as a jumping off point
but but because i came across yeah
because i came across so many sources in
my research
and many that this book didn't reference
i thought i wanted to go broader right
because this this book is
is fantastic starting point um
but but it it says nothing about what
i'm talking about
in terms of a paradigm shift right how
do we achieve mass
you know class consciousness and tipping
points and
all the sorts of fantastical
ideas of modernism right uh but they
definitely dovetail
you know there's there's um sort of uh
uh
um alignment with um you know
speculative realism and
and object-oriented ontology and all on
all that so
there's so much in here just in you know
the
they talk about poesis and um
you know a lucia and and
at some point there's some quotes there
about like the metanoia is kind of a
fundamental concept to philosophers
right okay
i think that i thank you for
recommending that i'm sorry i have not
come across that
that's awesome yeah yeah i i i i will
definitely order that book once
once we're done talking okay so i want
to give you space and like you
you'll probably say things that i might
not initially agree with
uh but but before i do that um before we
move to
like because i want i like
you've made a criticism of me and i take
and i tried to take it to heart
um and you said you know because i talk
a lot about
and you don't you don't dismiss this you
recognize it i talk a lot about bridging
between science and spirituality
but you say you know i think
appropriately yeah but what about
science and the political i have some
criticisms
uh of of that but i think you have a
more aristotelian sense of politics
than the current meaning of that term
maybe that's part of the we could work
out the semantics but the discussions
with layman and zach have sort of opened
me up
uh to at least what zach and layman have
been calling the meta-political
and so maybe you and i can initially i
mean at least maybe the two metas are
some common ground
the metanoia and the meta-political uh
but i will give you space for what you
want to say
but before i do that i wanted to ask you
about the perennialism because
like there's a there's a there's sort of
a thing going on in perennialism
there's sort of there's two versions of
it there's like sort of a ken wilber
version
right and then there's uh a jorge
ferreira version
and ferreira's version is that the
perennialism is
not one uh that everybody says has the
same thing
but that instead it's much more what i
would even call sort of
procedural perennialism the idea is that
uh there is a kind of knowing what i
call participatory knowing
that all of the religions are crafting
procedures
to try and get us to remember the
perspective of the participatory
and that that kind of perennialism i
think is viable
in concert with uh something like
pluralism
whereas i find the perennialism of
huxley for example
uh i find that very hard uh because
his seems well to use one of your terms
it seems very hegemonic
it seems like that all of these are
basically you know this particular
sort of christianized view of hinduism
that he had
and so i'm very sort of i'm sort of wary
of that
would you say that you're more of on
that side of perennialism the
the ferrer side than the huxley side it
just so
do i understand where you're coming from
um
did you swap out um wilbur for huxley
well i i i i see i see wilbur
as a as a modern version of huxley okay
okay yeah i mean are you talking about
all this huxley
yeah yes i mean i i love all this huxley
that's a good place to start but however
i think i think i'd lean more the other
way as
you're saying and what you're describing
you know evokes in me the the sociology
of religion so
within that subject right that that
merging of fields
they understand all of that stuff from a
functional point of view like what is
religion actually doing
as a form of social organization and um
and so i guess on the other hand you're
saying that um
the the wilbur huxley version is kind of
uh a bit more
abstracting it into a western context
and
a bit wishy-washy new age or prone for
misinterpretation
i i don't think i mean so for me i can't
find it
as easily alignable with sort of the
best cognitive science that i know
probably cognition wait culture and
cognition
what i call cultural cognitive grammar
works um
like so while i think you know and evan
thompson has made a very similar
argument in his recent book you know why
i'm not a buddhist
you know he he argues that um
western buddhism has basically sort of
crafted itself
uh to look like it's very scientific and
then claim that all of buddhism has
always been
more scientific uh and and and i think
so he rightly criticizes what he calls
buddhist exceptionalism
the idea that somehow buddhism you know
and i and i'm a friend of buddhism you
know that right but this is not a
hostile skeptic from the outside
the same thing would happen right i know
evan personally and so
that kind of exceptionalism what i'm
saying is there is a version i'm not
saying all versions
saying there's a version or a branch
maybe i'm doing something similar
like what you did with the modernism but
there's a branch of perennialism
that sort of allies itself with various
kinds of exceptionalisms
and that strikes me as i don't know if
you can make any kind of good
um justification for that move that's
what i'm criticizing
i think i understand um
sorry i got distracted because i was
trying to look up a world religions tree
yeah um and this is something i i came
across
a a long a long time ago but it's it
it came out of a a research project and
a foundation that
i think dovetails with what we're
talking about in you know trying to
you know first of all map everything but
then
uh from that sort of macro perspective
you can you can trace the origins and so
in in the tree
you know all the world religions do go
back
to uh not a single source
right but a kind of a kind of um a kind
of
weave a kind of trunk you know a threat
of sources and
and it's the same with languages right
and i'm fascinated with that idea too
because again we're talking about
pre-history
you know before written history kind of
culture
existed and it like it just
it was just extant it didn't exist in
the abstract it just was
you know i'm sure people had thoughts
and stuff but they didn't have
writing they didn't have um institutions
yet
they just they had language and so
that's mind-blowing
in itself and so you know with
metamodernism we're trying to trace this
long arc of history
uh and and you know not throw the baby
out with the bathwater
because all the all of these traditions
still have something to teach
i your language your language example
though is is really pertinent
so what i'm proposing is something not
like
not like that there is one
you know there's one best language let
let let's use the chomsky framework
i i i have criticisms of some of trump's
linguistics so
let's put it aside because right right
the idea of universal grammar that all
languages make use of
uh universal grammar but that doesn't
mean that all languages have the same
actual grammar and they work very
differently because they fit their
historical context
and you shouldn't use the notion of
universal grammar
to try and say somehow german
is a better language than spanish or
something like that and i hear people do
that
all the time they make exceptionalism
arguments like blah blah is a way more
complex language than blah blah yeah
and one of my criticism of heidegger by
the way is the way he get he he has that
kind of
exceptionalism towards german as the
best language in which one does
philosophy
or something like that and that for me
is like no that that's very problematic
so that's what i'm criticizing i i think
there's a universal
that you'll allow me the metaphor don't
don't push me too hard on it
i think there's a universal grammar for
religion but i think there are many
different religious languages
and the universal grammar is does not
give the basis
for privilege in any one of these
languages over the other that's what i'm
saying
yeah exactly and um so
so with that said like i want to go in
two directions
either simultaneously or or
you know one at a time but one is we
keep going in this broad
abstract direction but the other is you
know i wanted to touch on
christian metanoia because we can talk
about that within the bubble
yeah yes christianity right and so then
it's contextualized in that
that greater context um okay so if i
if i go there first um so my the point i
wanted to make though is like
i've always been uh a dabbler in the
different
religions and fields right and i'm i'm
not i'm not just co-opting to mash up
something i'm you know
each one has its own complexity and
depth yep
but i do think that at the end of the
day they're kind of they're kind of
dead ends like or cul-de-sacs rather you
know you got it you got to return to the
source
and um you know so so there's a within
christianity there's many traditions
right now i've gravitated towards
certain traditions more like gnostic
christianity right
so and and my take away from that is
that
you know god is kind of within and and
you can
you know i i don't mean in a crude sense
that you you have
uh direct gnostic access but in
a cognitive sense you're you're you know
you study and you enter the flow state
maybe you take some substances
uh and you have a gnostic experience
right which is your mind is
is lit up and it's integrating and
synthesizing all this information
right and so this is contemporary
language but
my understanding of the the jesus
metanoia
itself in in that time
and before i say this i want to preface
like jesus may not have existed
historically like there's there's
serious scholarly arguments
uh that that um you know that
deconstruct that notion and so i want to
give a kind of uh
just an honest take because
somebody like jordan peterson for
example waffles on this topic and thinks
maybe even jesus came back from the dead
and so i want to i want to draw a clear
line right and so i'm not disrespecting
christianity
i'm taking it to a higher level than
someone like jordan peterson you need to
historicize it
not that's my cat
um so so jesus may have existed
uh there may i wrote a paper once that
uh i
found there was many people named jesus
at that time and many
you know crucifixion was a a common
practice
so since there's nothing that's uh still
available
written about jesus at the time you know
nothing gives us any
real context you know eyewitness
accounts what is that
worth i'm just i want to start off on a
a clear speculative ground here right
sure
and i'm also going to preface and say
you know i'm not going to say you know
jesus was a socialist or whatever
because these are anachronistic
terms in that sense however
that is kind of what i'm saying is like
jesus was a rebel
a political rebel of his time
um and he was he was basically
persecuted and crucified for
um not just political crimes but
spiritual
blasphemy saying i am god and all this
right so the punchline that i'm getting
to is that the metanoia
of jesus and of all of christianity is
to realize the the
divine spark within everybody
and that and so you're taking away that
monotheistic
authority from the state and
bringing it into yourself right so jesus
as a jew
under roman rule is saying no uh excuse
me
i'm god you can't tell me otherwise
and so i really respect that that notion
right i mean
if christianity is about anything
fundamentally it hangs on that
and so this is why i i don't want to
fetishize the character of jesus at all
this we're talking about 2000 years ago
it's got nothing to do
with with you know the internet and
um you know modernity so we have to
you know again not throw the baby with
the bath water
but um recontextualize all these things
re-learn
and be it be it stop talking about
religion stop talking about this
or that figurehead but embody it and so
so
my own realizations have been along
those lines is
is not that i'm the messiah right there
is no messiah
but then i'm going to try to live up to
those principles and not the principles
as
as you know um sort of um
distilled by this or that church which
which can very easily be co-opted into a
a political agenda or whatever you know
or just as a mechanism of social control
but as this so to bring back this term
perennial is this perennial realization
yeah that divinity is within us all and
that we have to nurture that
and practice it practice it through
spirituality
and and if we're gonna have religion
uh and we're if we're gonna
institutionalize it then it needs to be
far far you know more ethical than what
we've seen
historically it needs to be totally
non-violent uh totally humanist
and this is what people like martin
luther king and gandhi
embodied and pursued with the same vigor
as a kind of christ figure
yeah that's wonderful so just uh you
recommended a book to me
did you have you read april the conic's
book uh the gnostic new age
uh because basically she's one of the
people there so the gnostics have
undergone um you probably are aware of
this they've undergone a sort of a
significant uh
revival and revisioning within
scholastic work
i mean so i mean not that it's not a
good book hundred donuts book
is i think a very important book but
since then there's been
a reinterpretation and some people are
even questioning whether there was ever
something like the gnostics
uh people argue that narcissism was and
i think there's
there's good evidence amounting to it
narcissism is much more
a style of any religion you're
practicing um they the comparison
that's often made is like narcissism is
a term like
it's not it's not the same term it's i'm
talking about what kind of term it is
it's the same kind of term as
fundamentalism
you can be a fundamentalist christian uh
fundamentalist muslim
cetera and narcissism is much more like
that i don't know if you know there's an
episode in my
uh series that i did on on gnosis and
narcissism and i've
done some talk on this but anyways one
of the things that
the brought out and
this is the way i i argued it i want to
know what you think about this because i
argue
that the gnostics and there's there's
problems with the gnostics they also
have a dark history
they go into the you know the european
underground and get associated
with all kinds of conspiracy theory crap
and there's there's been danger there
in their history but going back to what
you said
the the perennial quest i argued that
there's a sense in which the gnostics
are trying to complete the actual
revolution
because what the chronic argues is that
uh the exo revolution had already
done a significant change but
what she says is you know that the
transgressive nature
of gnosticism was that
it was calling into question something
that had been held over
from the pre-axial period into the
actual period
which was that the basic relationship
between human beings and the god
was one modeled on enslavement and
servitude
and that the gnostics were trying to
finish the axial revolution by
removing that and therefore seeing all
the existing gods
as uh representing that holdover
uh that that and so
and so you know and and this comes out
this comes out in places where people
might not expect
so here's you know he's of course
considered
you know uh radical in some sense but
he's nevertheless considered a mainline
an important theologian
paul tillich when paul talks about the
god beyond the god of theism
he's basically making that same argument
he's making the argument
that we haven't completed the actual
revolution if that's something we want
to do
but but nevertheless right because we're
still bound to this grammar
of sacredness and slavery being bound
together
and of course i think that does have all
kinds of metapolitical consequences
in it and so and yeah and you're right
jesus is crucified
and crucifixion is the punishment uh for
you know political threats to the roman
establishment let's not let's not forget
that
he i agree with you he's also criticized
he's also crucified
for religious reasons uh having to do
again here's a gnostic thing
he seems to be overthrowing purity codes
um and this was also part of the gnostic
thing that the purity codes that we live
by
are often ways in which we are bound
into things
you know you get this in jesus saying
things like you know the sabbath was
made for mankind
not mankind for the sabbath he's trying
to invert the relationship
um in a very fundamental way and so i
think
i i i i wanna this sorry this is long
i i'm sort of getting you though i'm
sort of getting why
that and this is honest and you know
it's respectful
and getting why you would be attracted
to
sort of the gnostic thread uh within
christianity
yeah and let me yeah there's a there's a
lot i want to pick up off there
and keep going um so yeah i agree
with you i'm not going to refute
anything about the the history of
gnosticism like there's many rabbit
holes there and what i'm attracted to is
is the knowledge part right the knowing
and so
as a you know a sociology person
um this is where it gets tangible and
and
interesting is like you know religion
and not just religion but
uh you know social organization in
general but
but religion in particular tries to
control knowledge and power
right that relationship yes it's always
been that way and so
to this day we have an epistemic crisis
where we
can't disentangle knowledge and power
and so
you know so it undermines scholarship
itself
because so much of uh scholarship and
scholasticism was created under these
conditions of power
and so history is the unfolding of that
and i do believe in some
abstract sense of a kind of
um uh well let's say completing the
axial age
but also you know fulfilling you know
hegel and marx's vision like so
there's there's an eschatology here yeah
and not necessarily
like like uh like a nihilistic one right
like this is
it's rel we can strive for relative
utopia
but um you know so i reject the kind of
you know
biblical eschatology but but it's
fascinating because
there was a a great flood in ancient
history right before writing
again and this was passed down through
through uh
yeah old tradition and all that i think
there's good callers around that i agree
yeah but we we we couldn't confirm it
until later science
right and then we you know and it's not
like we're finding noah's ark or
whatever like
yeah whatever but but there was a great
flood and sea levels rose like 400
feet whatever it was and um
uh you know and so it was for
you know humanity or whatever uh
collective consciousness existed
um in its in its primitive forms um
there was culture and there was a kind
of social imaginary
and that was destroyed and of course in
a smaller scale there's been many many
end times right this is a ubiquitous uh
recurrent
concept but what is different today
right and again putting aside like mine
calendar prophecies and stuff like that
putting you know
we we are in the kind of end times and
so i like this theme
uh because it's it's it's ubiquitous in
in in culture and
and and with with climate change with
the end of capitalism
uh these things are kind of kicking the
door
down and you know these things are like
confronting us and we have to confront
it
um so so my my broader point though is
that everything you said and what i'm
trying to say dovetails into this
political conversation was inescapable
because it defines the terms of
knowledge and power
and how they relate so um you know the
20th century
saw a lot of brutality but it also saw
the expansion
of these progressive humanist
institutions but they're still not
universal we're still debating things
like
systemic racism like the extent of it
and
there's people who deny it uh and and
you know white supremacy is a
is a latent invisible thing um
that acts through people uh
sometimes unconsciously through and
through institutions
and so this kind of stuff this kind of
lower level stuff
actually prevents us from solving the
greater problem right and we have to
solve
all the problems in an integrated
fashion is that yeah
yeah yeah um so
so um yeah coming back to this idea of
gnosis like
like i think for myself and probably a
lot of people who
who study and practice these things you
eventually you have to take
responsibility for it yourself and
figure it out yourself right so um
so i guess for me it's been a quest of
of extracting
uh knowledge from
uh from a given context like
trying trying to learn things firsthand
as impossible as that is
you know like when it comes to politics
you need to decode a lot of
nonsense and so uh and you have to be
kind of spiritually grounded at the same
time so you can
um i guess differentiate
uh different qualities of information
can i can i can
can i pick up on that in one concrete
example from my own work
because when you're invoking the the
eschaton and the apocalypse
i mean so chris and philip and i wrote
in the book you know about the zombie
apocalypse
and the problem about the zombie
apocalypse is right is it
it's a perversion of of apocalypse right
the
apocalypse originally meant revelation
it meant something like
a worldwide insight a metanoia
on at a civilization level uh so that
the world
and the asian arena relationship to use
my language or our language
i mean my co-authors is radically
transformed
and a viable long-term future
is now made possible in a way it wasn't
before the the
myth is you have decadence and it can
right and
the only future is a decadent one and
then you get this metanoia
that's systemic across the civilization
and then
a viable future becomes available but
the point about the zombie apocalypse
is it articulate it expresses without
articulation so
i misspoke it expresses without
articulation the meaning crisis
and how it's infecting our notion and
basically shutting it down
because what the zombie apocalypse is is
it's the perversion the zombie is the
perversion of the resurrection
the zombie apocalypse is not a viable
future it's a future
that is continually decaying everything
is being every
and so what i'm what what i'm saying to
you is
like you mentioned that decoding
and it and maybe this won't be how you
would use your work with this word but i
would use this word
here and what i'm learning from zach and
um
layman i think there's a meta-political
project of decoding
that perversion of the myth and showing
people
that you know that it's it's there's a
kind of
it's very attractive that goes without
question
but it's attractive in a way that's
entrapping and it's preventing
right it's preventing the kind of
transformation
we need in order to try and bring about
a viable future now is that an example
of the kind of thing we're talking about
where like we're we're like i was trying
to get it go go people
we were trying to get people to see this
myth
because i don't believe in mythology yes
you believe in this
you believe in this and you enact it and
you will do these huge
social rituals going on zombie walks and
dressing up like zombies yeah
right but you're not you'll allow me
your verb again you're not decoding this
you're not seeing what's being
articulated in here
and you're not and and worse you're not
seeing
what's being perpetuated yeah in this
mythos
and how it's hamstringing you in a very
very powerful way
so i have this ambivalent attitude
towards the zombie apocalypse
i mean i think it's important as a
phenomenon but i think
people need to decode it and understand
yeah what it's doing
is that is that a fair example i'm
trying to yeah it's a great
work it's a great example because i've
thought about
the zombie apocalypse a fair bit i
haven't written about it yet but we'll
see
let me see if i can just explain my
thoughts because
because uh yeah zombie culture is big
you know i'm not a big [ __ ] buff
there's there's lots out there but i
like i like i like meta humor so for
example you take the movie shawn of the
dead
yeah he's very popular kind of kind of
play on zombie films right
and so i love that kind of stuff but so
for me
you know the so the the the cultural
depiction of zombies is like the living
dead
and they eat brains and all this and
it's it's ironic because what i see is
zombie culture
and i have no doubt there's a lot
written on this
but zombie culture is like consumerism
so you're so kind of mindless
just droning around and you know um
and the idea of eating brains is ironic
too
because it's like this longing for
knowledge but you don't want to
work you want to take the shortcut and
just nourish yourself
cannibalizing somebody else right so a
lot of these sort of myths wherever they
originate from they do kind of uh
layer and complicate some simpler truth
like in the case of zombies it's like
you know it's maybe a a death denial
mechanism and
it it sub serves functions and
sublimates all these things and
entertains us but if we're to decode it
i would say the zombie apocalypse would
be
you know just people who are
sort of uncritically uh drifting through
the world
yeah even if they're very smart you know
if they're just mindless consumers
that the zombie apocalypse is awakening
from that
right and and breaking the mold that
you're in and
and um issuing those habits
right and and eschewing the the
literalism of the myth
yes right always looking at the deeper
level
yeah and and it seems like you know
coming back to mass metanoia it's it's
it seems like we're not getting any
closer you know like there's things like
the zeitgeist movement and
other things like that which are trying
to build mass consciousness
and a kind of political cultural
meta-narrative uh
which in large part is perennial it's
it's like the interesting thing about
the zeitgeist movement is that it was
you know consciously kind of theatrical
and vaudevillian and
yeah and it and it and it merged all
these religions and said look well the
the myths of jesus is just like horus or
whatever and
you know so it was kind of
meta-historical um
but ultimately like
i wanted and you know i i strive for
these things to dovetail more like i
don't think the zeitgeist movement in
itself
has any kind of conclusion it's all a
prelude to some
institutional change like we're all and
this is why i believe in convergence it
needs to
it needs to dovetail more and not more
people start more spin-off projects
yeah yeah yeah um and so uh and none of
it is perfect right we have to take the
best of each
of each thing and so yeah
that's my riff on the zombie idea so
that's great
that's great um we're sort of coming to
the end of the hour
so i don't know if i want to start
another big topic but i'd like to invite
you to come back
and we continue um yeah we we got
started a little late so
i don't think we've been talking that
long um
it's up to you of course in your
availability but we can keep going how
about
i'm not saying we stop right now but i i
i have about i have about
five more minutes okay and
and and you know starting late was my
fault and i apologize
no problem but like so but i
i think there's momentum what we're
talking about it and so like i'm
extending the
invitation so i'm not trying to close
this off okay going
yeah going i just i just like with it
feels like also there's a bit of a
we've come like this topic has been come
to
sort of like a point of coherence for me
in my mind understanding where you're
coming from a lot more clearly now
than i did in a previous discussion um
so
i'm just also worried about sort of the
logical thing if we start something and
it's about five minutes and
yeah a dangler i'm inviting you to come
back
and we get more but what i would like to
do then
is is give you the last five minutes
to you to whatever last word you want to
say about this
so that you don't feel like i've just
foreclosed on on
what's happened between us i thought
today was really good i mean i really
like what happened here i thought
there was some really good unpacking
gear i felt that
in turn i mean in terms of
um the manner i thought this was much
much better than
our previous recording right i think it
was much more flowy and dialogical
and so i thought and it felt much more
organic to me yeah great thanks
i don't know if you experienced it that
way but that's how i experienced it yeah
yeah it felt good and um
don't know what my my closing thoughts
would be um
what else have i not have we not touched
on there's lots more to go on metanoia
of course
it's yeah there is yeah
there's you know i mean just so we
didn't really define
all aspects of it at the outset so i'll
return to that
because one of the key
sort of uh basic parts of the definition
is that it's a transformation not just
of the self
but of the world as well totally and
of your future and your past perception
yeah and so
you know i i it's so potentially so hard
to define in a way that everyone's going
to relate to you know in my draft i kind
of touch on a lot of examples like it
could be
you know you you realize a conflict of
interest or
you know you you realize you did
something wrong or you atoned for your
your past sins and you know i try to
draw in some concrete examples like
christian picciolini for example is uh
he was an
ex neo-nazi you know
and like american history x right like
this is a guy who who went in head first
and
uh no pun intended and and he so he came
out on the other side
uh an anti-white supremacist speaker
right so
so it's a it's you know enantio dromio
like it's a complete inversion
of who he was in the best possible sense
because you go from being a nazi to an
anti-nazi
right and
um you know and so
you know we're all we're all nested in
in
systems of control in one way or another
right
and we're all through scarcity whether
it's real scarcity or artificial
scarcity
um we're compelled to do things that
aren't good uh fundamentally and i don't
just mean like killing or stealing
like part of my moral system
where i think i think some people aren't
aren't there yet quite frankly and it's
not it's not um an elitist thing
it's just that i i think more
sociologically more systemically
and so i think of ethics and agency is
nested in these systems
and so the only way to be moral is to
completely
extricate yourself and in a sense that's
impossible
but at least intellectually
um you need to is and so like i'm an
anti-war
kind of advocate right and so you can't
take a more
extreme position and a more alienating
and ostracizing position because people
just want to argue
with you or
sorry they want to argue with you about
war yeah
yeah yeah they want to they want to you
know
um equivocate and get you know get get
lost in the details
like like i i it just baffles me and
you know it's not that i'm a a pacifist
like if you go deep down that rabbit
hole
uh there's some push back there too
because like there's always this
argument at the end of the day like well
you got to defend yourself and you you
know if you're being invaded blah blah
blah
and so something we touched on in our
last conversation i think
is social paradox yeah yeah so i always
come back to that
idea too because it it traps people
right and if you're gonna get into an
argument
with me or with whoever about war
uh it's paradoxical right so there's
always arguments you can
you can scrape together for war for
militarization for conflict for
police brutality whatever and
and um you know so so i try to be
radical
in the most radical sense of
christianity that's that's a truly
emancipatory and truly non-violent
right and so you're i'm trying to
institutionalize
um love which is something that zach
talks about and
but but we need you can't you know it's
it's a difficult thing we can't just
practice it as individuals you need to
put your money where your mouth is you
need to advocate for the policies
that that uh fulfill the highest ideals
of
of religion and philosophy and whatnot
you mentioned gandhi and martin luther
king
are they examples of what you're talking
about right now this kind of
you know not just individual but also
collective um
and in in you know at least culturally
revolutionary
right um kind of non-violence but it's
not it's not a
it's not a passive non-violence right
it's an active
you know it's confrontational it's
trying to provoke transformation and
change
is that the kind of thing you're talking
about because you invoked them earlier
as well yeah
it is and it isn't it isn't because they
embedded themselves in
modern religion right religious
traditions to
affect these changes and i would say
in the case of gandhi not so much king
but in gandhi
it's like there's there's no fault of
gandhi's but
there's debate over the ultimate effect
right so
this is a topic for another day but like
by
by india achieving independence um
that that led into different periods of
decline
within india and i i traveled there i
read some some books on india and so
it's not a clear topic like they they
revere him and also criticize him
yeah um so the modern difference with
with these things
is is in part that we have to do it a
little different but also like
invest less in the figureheads and i
mean
choose the right people to follow but
there's there's such a responsibility
at the individual level like we have to
have to have to have a much more
distributed
cognition as you would say yes but one
that is at a
at a sort of high level that we
we don't we don't equivocate we don't
fall for
ruses we don't you know play into these
fallacies and traps
because we're all this is what politics
does because it's a power game
it ends up co-opting people and that's
why highly intelligent people like
yourself
want to step away from it or want to do
meta politics
right but i would close with the point
to challenge you and as well as zach and
layman
to you know to do the harder thing which
is to join me in the ongoing literacy
of of leftist and progressive and
socialist politics you actually know
what's going on
because you can't trust virtually
anybody in the media ecosystems
except the people who are consistent and
advocating for the universalist policies
right so common expression and defense
of leftism
is that uh you know that we're in fact
just advocating for what are now
mainstream policies
so the the left should be the new center
not
whatever is happening in the current
center
uh with with biden and kamala harris and
and unit you know quote unquote unity
projects and
um it's really you know getting back to
basics universal healthcare universal
education
uh you know with with the nut with a
kind of
uh a buffet of policy instruments like
ubi and modern monetary theory that
enable this paradigm shift well as we
get closer
layman did bring up ubi and other things
yeah right he was talking about that
and so i'm just just just to defend him
a little bit
sure yeah there's lots of puzzle pieces
floating out there
and you know andrew yang is for ubi and
i like him
in so far as he's for that but and and
he'll and he likes bernie
you know but what happened over the last
five years politically
is just a mess uh and i and i blame
the i blame a lot of people
who refused to participate
in that discourse and that movement
right
and and in one sense it's never too late
you know
but but we we keep missing these windows
and so um we need to converge
right we need all these different uh
discourses and communities and political
movements
to actually consolidate and it has to
consolidate under the authentic
progressive leadership
which is somebody like bernie sanders
right even though he's not running for
president anymore
he's still active and he's still an
important
politician and leader and so the way
these things fall apart and get
fragmented so easily
is not for lack of trying right it's
because of the way
power operates and through and capital
through
media institutions and uh think tanks
and
you know all of these people hanging on
to their power
and i guess maybe a way to bring it back
to religion and to close it out
is like uh you know these are
you know kind of death denial mechanisms
again and
we have to recognize how you know our
own our own mortality our own collective
mortality and there's literally nothing
to to cling to except these
these universal values you know that is
what moves the needle
and that is what that is what goodness
fundamentally is if
we want to get really deep into the core
of religion
you know we got to throw at the
hypocrites and we got to take
responsibility without becoming
those uh powerful
those powerful people that become
hypocrites again like yeah i agree
we need to we need to maintain that
spiritual integrity
in the face of death and
and um so you know
i see lots of people uh taking you know
different different long you know
not shortcuts but like the long way
around because they don't want to cut
they don't want to do the right thing
and the
the right thing intellectually and
morally is to converge on the best
uh universal kind of policies and and
to work through the differences you know
just if
if if we're gonna worship anything
and practice anything um
it it can dovetail with this bigger
picture the the more time we waste
um kind of like
competitive you know doing competitive
um
commentary or philosophy uh the more
people die
you know a thought that that keeps
coming into my in my head is like how
many palestinians have to die
until we until we take the right course
of action because this is a
a very transparently kind of black and
white issue
uh for me and for the international
community and for the for the left
but the discourse gets gets mangled and
co-opted continually by
um people like benjamin netanyahu right
they just they're they're they're
they're neo-fascists and so
i said this word literacy like we need
to we need to come back and have an
honest
deep literacy about politics history
economics
the way all these these things
interconnect because what is undermining
that is the continued potency of the
narratives
coming from people like trump people
like biden
you know and all across the the spectrum
with the exception
of the emergent left
right who's just trying to advocate for
health care
you know things that are human rights so
again this idea of
fulfillment of history whether it's the
new axial age or
or whatever i think these these
uh the truth in these notions
fundamentally converges
rather than uh and endlessly
proliferates
in different directions
well thank you uh thank you for your
challenge um
i i i do think i'm trying to
do good in the world in the ways you're
talking about but
uh but nevertheless um i do appreciate
your your passion and and
and your and your perspective um and i
do think there's something deeply right
about uh the project of convergence that
you're talking about
um and so that does seem to
be a good place then to bring things to
a close uh because
of the metaphor of conversions um so i
do i do think we should talk again
and i think that would be great uh but
um
i think we should end it for today and i
want to thank you for coming in
and um like i said uh
i thought your you made your position uh
really deep for me uh which i really
appreciate it so thank you very much for
that
thank you john and thank you the
audience uh whoever's out there
okay